Flies. Chapter 3. Huts on the Beach.
Jack was bent double. He was down like a sprinter, his nose only a few inches
from the humid earth. The tree trunks and the creepers that foned them lost
themselves in a green dusk 30 ft above him, and all about was the undergrowth.
There was only the faintest indication of betrayal here, a cracked twig and
what might be the impression of one side of a hoof. He lowered his chin and
stared at the traces as though he would force them to speak to him. Then
doglike, uncomfortably on all fours, yet unheeding his discomfort, he stole
forward 5 yards and stopped. Here was loop of creeper with a tendril pendant
from a node. The tendril was polished on the underside. Pigs passing through the
loop brushed it with their bristly hide.
Jack crouched with his face a few inches away from this clue, then stared forward
into the semi- darkness of the undergrowth. His sandy hair, considerably longer than it had been
when they had dropped in, was lighter now, and his bare back was a mass of
dark freckles and peeling sunburn. A sharpened stick about 5t long trailed
from his right hand, and except for a pair of tattered shorts held up by his
knife belt, he was naked. He closed his eyes, raised his head, and breathed in
gently with flared nostrils, assessing the current of warm air for information.
The forest and he were very still. At length he let out his breath in a long
sigh and opened his eyes. They were bright blue eyes that in this
frustration seemed bolting and nearly mad. He passed his tongue across dry
lips and scanned the unccommunicative forest. Then again he stole forward and
cast this way and that over the ground.
The silence of the forest was more impressive than the heat, and at this
hour of the day there was not even the wind of insects. Only when Jack himself
roused a goddy bird from a primitive nest of sticks was the silence
shattered, and echoes set ringing by a harsh cry that seemed to come out of the
abyss of ages. Jack himself shrank at this cry with a hiss of indrawn breath,
and for a minute became less a hunter than a furt of thing, ape-like among the
tangle of trees. Then the trail, the frustration, claimed him again, and he
searched the ground avidly. By the trunk of a vast tree that grew pale flowers on
its gray bark, he checked, closed his eyes, and once more drew in the warm
air, and this time his breath came short. There was even a passing pour in
his face, and then the surge of blood again. He passed like a shadow under the
darkness of the tree, and crouched, looking down at the trotten ground at
his feet. The droppings were warm. They lay piled among turned earth. They were
olive green, smooth, and they steamed a little. Jack lifted his head and stared
at the inscrable masses of creeper that lay across the trail. Then he raised his
spear and sneaked forward. Beyond the creeper, the trail joined a pig run that
was wide enough and trodden enough to be a path. The ground was hardened by an
accustomed tread, and as Jack rose to his full height, he heard something
moving on it. He swung back his right arm and hurled the spear with all his
strength. From the pig run came the quick, hard patter of hoofs. A castanet
sound, seductive, maddening, the promise of meat. He rushed out of the
undergrowth and snatched up his spear.
The pattering of pigs trotters died away in the distance. Jack stood there,
streaming with sweat, streaked with brown earth, stained by all the
vicissitudes of a day's hunting.
Swearing, he turned off the trail and pushed his way through until the forest
opened a little, and instead of bald trunks supporting a dark roof, there
were light gray trunks and crowns of feathery palm. Beyond these was the
glitter of the sea, and he could hear voices. Ralph was standing by a
contraption of palm trunks and leaves, a rude shelter that faced the lagoon, and
seemed very near to falling down. He did not notice when Jack spoke. "Got any
water?" Ralph looked up, frowning from the complication of leaves. He did not
notice Jack even when he saw him. I said, "Have you got any water? I'm
thirsty. Ralph withdrew his attention from the shelter and realized Jack with
a start. Oh, hello. Water there by the tree. Ought to be some left. Jack took
up a coconut shell that brimmed with fresh water from among a group that was
arranged in the shade and drank. The water splashed over his chin and neck
and chest. He breathed noisily when he had finished. Needed that. Simon spoke
from inside the shelter. Up a bit. Ralph turned to the shelter and lifted a
branch with a whole tiling of leaves.
The leaves came apart and fluttered down. Simon's contrite face appeared in
the hole. Sorry. Ralph surveyed the wreck with distaste. Never get it done.
He flung himself down at Jack's feet.
Simon remained, looking out of the hole in the shelter. Once down, Ralph
explained, "Been working for days now.
And look, two shelters were in position, but shaky. This one was a ruin. And they
keep running off. You remember the meeting how everyone was going to work
hard until the shelters were finished?
Except me and my hunters. Except the hunters. Well, the little ones are," he
justiculated, sought for a word.
"They're hopeless. The older ones aren't much better. Do you see? All day I've
been working with Simon. No one else.
They're off bathing or eating or playing. Simon poked his head out
carefully. You're chief. You tell them off. Ralph lay flat and looked up at the
palm trees in the sky. Meetings. Don't we love meetings? Every day, twice a
day, we talk. He got on one elbow. I bet if I blew the conchk this minute, they'd
come running. Then we'd be, you know, very solemn and someone would say, "We
ought to build a jet or a submarine or a TV set." When the meeting was over,
they'd work for 5 minutes, then wander off or go hunting. Jack flushed. We want
meat. Well, we haven't got any yet, and we want shelters. Besides, the rest of
your hunters came back hours ago.
They've been swimming. I went on, said Jack. I let
them go. I had to go on. I He tried to convey the compulsion to track down and
kill that was swallowing him up. I went on. I thought by myself. The madness
came into his eyes again. I thought I might kill, but you didn't. I thought I
might. Some hidden passion vibrated in Ralph's voice, "But you haven't yet."
His invitation might have passed as casual were it not for the undertone.
"You wouldn't care to help with the shelters, I suppose. We want meat, and
we don't get it." Now, the antagonism was audible. But I shall next time. I've
got to get a barb on this spear. We wounded a pig, and the spear fell out.
If we could only make barbs. We need shelters. Suddenly, Jack shouted in
rage. "Are you accusing? All I'm saying is we worked dashed hard, that's all."
They were both red in the face and found looking at each other difficult. Ralph
rolled on his stomach and began to play with the grass. If it rains like when we
dropped in, we'll need shelters. All right. And then another thing. We need
shelters because of the He paused for a moment, and they both pushed their anger
away. Then he went on with the safe, changed subject. You've noticed, haven't
you? Jack put down his spear and squatted. Noticed what? Well, they're
frightened. He rolled over and peered into Jack's fierce, dirty face. I mean,
the way things are. They dream. You can hear them. Have you been awake at night?
Jack shook his head. They talk and scream. The little onins, even some of
the others. As if, as if it wasn't a good island. Astonished at the
interruption, they looked up at Simon's serious face. As if, said Simon, the
beasty. The beasty or the snake thing was real. Remember? The two older boys
flinched when they heard the shameful syllable. Snakes were not mentioned now.
Were not mentionable. As if this wasn't a good island, said Ralph slowly. Yes,
that's right. Jack sat up and stretched out his legs. They're baddy crackers.
Remember when we went exploring? They grinned at each other, remembering the
glamour of the first day. Ralph went on.
So, we need shelters as a sort of home.
That's right. Jack drew up his legs, clasped his knees, and frowned in an
effort to attain clarity. All the same, in the forest. I mean, when you're
hunting, not when you're getting fruit, of course, but when you're on your own.
He paused for a moment, not sure if Ralph would take him seriously. Go on.
If you're hunting, sometimes you catch yourself feeling as if he flushed
suddenly. There's nothing in it, of course, just a feeling. But you can feel
as if you're not hunting, but being hunted, as if something's behind you all
the time in the jungle. They were silent again, Simon intent. Ralph incredulous
and faintly indignant. He sat up, rubbing one shoulder with a dirty hand.
Well, I don't know. Jack leapt to his feet and spoke very quickly. That's how
you can feel in the forest. Of course, there's nothing in it. Only Only He took
a few rapid steps toward the beach, then came back. Only I know how they feel.
See, that's all. The best thing we can do is get ourselves rescued. Jack had to
think for a moment before he could remember what rescue was. Rescue? Yes,
of course. All the same, I'd like to catch a pig first. He snatched up his
spear and dashed it into the ground. The opaque mad look came into his eyes
again. Ralph looked at him critically through his tangle of fair hair. So long
as your hunters remember the fire. You and your fire.
The two boys trotted down the beach and turning at the water's edge, looked back
at the pink mountain. The trickle of smoke sketched a chalky line up the
solid blue of the sky, wavered high up and faded. Ralph frowned. I wonder how
far off you could see that miles. We don't make enough smoke. The bottom part
of the trickle, as though conscious of their gaze thickened to a creamy blur
which crept up the feeble column.
They've put on green branches, muttered Ralph. I wonder. He screwed up his eyes
and swung round to search the horizon.
Got it! Jack shouted so loudly that Ralph jumped. "What? Where? Is it a
ship?" But Jack was pointing to the high declivities that led down from the
mountain to the flatter part of the island. "Of course they'll lie up there.
They must when the sun's too hot." Ralph gazed, bewildered at his wrapped face.
"They get up high, high up and in the shade, resting during the heat like cows
at home. I thought you saw a ship." "We could steal up on one, paint our faces
so they wouldn't see, perhaps surround them, and then indignation took away
Ralph's control. I was talking about smoke. Don't you want to be rescued? All
you can talk about is pig, pig, pig. But we want meat, and I work all day with
nothing but Simon, and you come back and don't even notice the huts. I was
working, too. But you like it, shouted Ralph. You want to hunt while I They
faced each other on the bright beach, astonished at the rub of feeling. Ralph
looked away first, pretending interest in a group of little ones on the sand.
From beyond the platform came the shouting of the hunters in the swimming
pool. On the end of the platform, Piggy was lying flat, looking down into the
brilliant water. People don't help much.
He wanted to explain how people were never quite what you thought they were.
Simon, he helps. He pointed at the shelters. All the rest rushed
off. He's done as much as I have. Only Simon's always about. Ralph started back
to the shelters with Jack by his side.
Do a bit for you, muttered Jack before I have a bathe. Don't bother. But when
they reached the shelters, Simon was not to be seen. Ralph put his head in the
hole, withdrew it, and turned to Jack.
He's buzzed off. Got fed up, said Jack, and gone for a bathe. Ralph frowned.
He's queer. He's funny. Jack nodded as much for the sake of agreeing as
anything. And by tacic consent, they left the shelter and went toward the
bathing pool. And then, said Jack, when I've had a bathe and something to eat,
I'll just trek over to the other side of the mountain and see if I can see any
traces. Coming? But the sun's nearly set. I might have time. They walked
along two continents of experience and feeling, unable to communicate. If I
could only get a pig, I'll come back and go on with the shelter. They looked at
each other, baffled in love and hate.
All the warm salt water of the bathing pool, and the shouting and splashing and
laughing were only just sufficient to bring them together
again. Simon was not in the bathing pool as they had expected. When the other two
had trotted down the beach to look at the mountain, he had followed them for a
few yards and then stopped. He had stood frowning down at a pile of sand on the
beach where somebody had been trying to build a little house or hut. Then he
turned his back on this and walked into the forest with an air of purpose. He
was a small, skinny boy, his chin pointed, and his eyes so bright they had
deceived Ralph into thinking him delightfully gay and wicked. The coarse
mop of black hair was long and swung down, almost concealing a low, broad
forehead. He wore the remains of shorts, and his feet were bare like Jack's,
always darkish in color. Simon was burned by the sun to a deep tan that glistened with sweat.
He picked his way up the scar, past the great rock where Ralph had climbed on
the first morning, then turned off to his right among the trees. He walked
with an accustomed tread through the acres of fruit trees, where the least
energetic could find an easy, if unsatisfying, meal. Flower and fruit
grew together on the same tree, and everywhere was the scent of ripess and
the booming of a million bees at pasture. Here the little ones who had
run after him caught up with him. They talked, cried out unintelligably, lugged
him toward the trees. Then, amid the roar of bees in the afternoon sunlight,
Simon found for them the fruit they could not reach, pulled off the choicest
from up in the foliage, passed them back down to the endless outstretched hands.
When he had satisfied them, he paused and looked round. The little onins
watched him incredibly over double handfuls of ripe fruit. Simon turned
away from them and went where the just perceptible path led him. Soon high
jungle closed in. Tall trunks bore unexpected pale flowers all the way up
to the dark canopy where life went on clamorously.
The air here was dark, too, and the creepers dropped their ropes like the
rigging of foundered ships. His feet left prince in the soft soil, and the
creepers shivered throughout their lengths when he bumped them. He came at
last to a place where more sunshine fell. Since they had not so far to go
for light, the creepers had woven a great mat that hung at the side of an
open space in the jungle, for here a patch of rock came close to the surface,
and would not allow more than little plants and ferns to grow. The whole
space was walled with dark aromatic bushes, and was a bowl of heat and
light. A great tree fallen across one corner, leaned against the trees that
still stood, and a rapid climber flaunted red and yellow sprays right to
the top. Simon paused. He looked over his shoulder, as Jack had done, at the
close ways behind him, and glanced swiftly round to confirm that he was
utterly alone. For a moment, his movements were almost fertive. Then he
bent down and wormed his way into the center of the mat. The creepers in the
bushes were so close that he left his sweat on them, and they pulled together
behind him. When he was secure in the middle, he was in a little cabin,
screened off from the open space by a few leaves. He squatted down, parted the
leaves, and looked out into the clearing. Nothing moved but a pair of
goddy butterflies that danced around each other in the hot air. Holding his
breath, he cocked a critical ear at the sounds of the island. Evening was
advancing toward the island. The sounds of the bright fantastic birds, the bee
sounds, even the crying of the gulls that were returning to their roosts
among the square rocks were fainter. The deep sea breaking miles away on the reef
made an undertone less perceptible than the susation of the blood. Simon dropped
the screen of leaves back into place.
The slope of the bars of honeycolored sunlight decreased. They slid up the
bushes, passed over the green candle-like buds moved up toward the
canopy, and darkness thickened under the trees. With the fading of the light, the
riotous colors died, and the heat and urgency cooled away. The candle buds
stirred. Their green seepil drew back a little, and the white tips of the
flowers rose delicately to meet the open air. Now the sunlight had lifted clear
of the open space and withdrawn from the sky. Darkness poured out, submerging the
ways between the trees till they were dim and strange as the bottom of the
sea. The candle buds opened their white white flowers glimmering under the light
that pricricked down from the first stars. Their scent spilled out into the
air and took possession of the island. Lord of the